Guide to the School of Engineering Reference Collection, 1913-2014 UA.01.11.0019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
School of Engineering Reference collection
1913-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
UA.01.11.0019
0.7 Linear Feet
The Pratt School of Engineering traces its history back to 1851 when Normal College, a forerunner of Duke University, advertised a Classical course which included engineering for seniors. The School of Engineering Reference Collection contains files of clippings, articles, bulletins, reports, publications, and other materials about the School of Engineering.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The School of Engineering Reference Collection was compiled from various sources by University Archives staff for reference and research.
Historical Note
taken from Pratt School of Engineering website: http://www.pratt.duke.edu/about/history.php
The Pratt School of Engineering traces its history back to 1851 when Normal College, a forerunner of Duke University, advertised a Classical course which included engineering for seniors. Normal College became Trinity College in 1859 and engineering was introduced in 1887 and became a regular course offering in 1903.
When Trinity became Duke University in 1924, engineering underwent vigorous development.
Chronology List
1927 Civil and Electrical Engineering departments were established.
Classrooms/labs located in Asbury building on East campus. Engineering students were housed in Southgate building on East campus.
1931 Mechanical Engineering department established.
1937 Departments of CE, EE, and ME were administratively grouped to form the Division of Engineering.
1939 The University incorporated the Division of Engineering into the College of Engineering.
1946 First women to graduate from the College of Engineering: Muriel Theodorsen Williams (EE) and Marie Foote Reel (EE).
1947 Male Engineering students relocated to West Campus.
1948 College of Engineering moves to West Campus and begins classes in new Engineering Building (Old Red), now Hudson Hall.
1960 Doctor of Philosophy degree first offered in Electrical Engineering.
1964 Doctor of Philosophy first offered in Civil Engineering.
1966 College of Engineering changed to School of Engineering.
1968 First black engineers to graduate from School of Engineering: Kenneth Spaulding Chestnut (CE) and Alfred J. Hooks (ME).
1971 Department of Biomedical Engineering established — First BME Department established at a university in the United States — set the stage nationally for other BME Departments.
1984 Nello L. Teer Library Building opens.
1992 Engineering building, (Old Red) named Hudson Hall to honor Fitzgerald S. "Jerry" Hudson E'46.
1994 Levine Science Research Center opens.
1999 Kristina M. Johnson becomes first woman dean.
Duke University School of Engineering named the Edmund T. Pratt Jr. School of Engineering for Edmund T. Pratt Jr. E'47.
2004 Construction was completed on the Center for Interdisciplinary Engineering, Medicine and Applied Sciences in August. Pratt hosts dedication on November 18, 2004. Duke's Board of Trustees approve renaming CIEMAS in honor of Michael and Patty Fitzpatrick. CIEMAS is now formally known as the Fitzpatrick Center for Interdisciplinary Engineering, Medicine and Applied Sciences, informally dubbed the Fitzpatrick Center.
Related Material
Aleksandar Sedmak Vesic papers, circa 1950-1982.
University Archives, Duke University.
American Society of Civil Engineers, Duke University Chapter records, 1932-1983 (bulk 1944-1970).
University Archives, Duke University.
Otto Meier, Jr., records and papers, 1931-1979.
University Archives. Duke University.
School of Engineering records, 1931-1998.
University Archives, Duke University.
Collection Overview
The School of Engineering Reference Collection contains files of clippings, articles, bulletins, reports, publications, and other materials about the School of Engineering. This collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research.
Engineering -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University -- Students; Duke University. School of Engineering; Duke University. School of Engineering -- History; Duke University. School of Engineering -- Alumni and alumnae -- Directories; Pratt School of Engineering (Duke University)
- Administration, 1927-1978 (Box 1)
- Alumni Memoirs, 1990 (includes short statements from Marie Foote Reel and Muriel Theodorsen Williams the first female graduates in Engineering) (Box 1)
- Assemblies, 1953-1979 (Box 1)
- Catalogs and Bulletins, 1935-1989 (three folders) (Box 1)
- Classes, Class of ____ (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1931- (Box 1)
- Egg Drop Contest, 1978- (Box 1)
- Engineering Club, 1913-1914 (Box 1)
- Freshman Engineer Handbooks, 1950-1977 (Box 1)
- Engineering Faculty Council, 2001 (Box 1)
- History, General, 1943, 1999 (Box 1)
- Society of Women Engineers, undated (Box 1)
- The Engineering Dispatch [newsletter], 1994 (Box 1)
- Alumni Newsletter, 1963, 1966 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous publications
  - The Dukengineer (Box 1)
  - Engineering Horizons, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Research reports (Box 1)
  - Progress Report, 2005 (Box 1)
- Biochemical Engineering, Center for, 1988- (Box 1)
- Biochemical, Dept. of. 1970- (Box 1)
- Teer Library Dedication, 1984 (Box 1)
- Teer Library Groundbreaking, 1982 (Box 1)
- Civil and Environmental Engineering (Box 1)
- Civil and Environmental Engineering [newsletter] (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Civil and Environmental Engineering, brochures, etc. (Box 1)
- Electrical Engineering, Graduate Study, 1965- (Box 1)
- Mechanical Engineering, 1950-1965 (Box 1)
- Engineers' Club (Box 1)